A Guide to the Samuel J. Meltzer papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA180
Rockefeller Archive Center
Samuel J. Meltzer papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Meltzer, Samuel James
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA180
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 M496
Scope and Contents
Business Manager files and other items.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Physiology; Diseases; Pathology; Pharmacology; Medical research; Medical sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Biology -- Research; Life sciences; Meltzer, Samuel James; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Biographical Material, 1918-1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Printed Memoirs.
  - "Division of Physiology and Pharmacology", 1918-1919
    [1918-1919 staff budget and information on staff moves]. Last complete budget for the division.
  - New York Times? clipping, "Dr. Samuel Meltzer, Physiologist, Dies", 1920 November 5; Photocopy
  - Memorial number for S.J. Meltzer, printed addresses given at a meeting of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1921 January 6
  - W.H. Howell, "Samuel James Meltzer", Science 53 (1921) 99. Biographical memoir clipping
  - J.J.A., "Samuel James Meltzer", Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, 1921 April; 2 pp.
  - William H. Howell, "Biographical Memoir Samuel James Meltzer 1851-1920", Memoirs of the National Academy of Sciences 21 (1927) 1-23, Reprint
- Bibliography, 1880-1920; 28 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Administrative correspondence, 1904-1920
  Scope and Contents
  The item list is comprised of selected items.
  - S.J. Meltzer/L. Emmett Holt, acknowledgement of appoint as Associate, 1904 June 23 1904 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    beginning October 1, 1904 for one year
  - Meltzer/Simon Flexner, re Meltzer's relations to the Institute, 1905 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meltzer/L. Emmett Holt, thank you for election as a Member and appointment as head of Department of Physiology and Pharmacology, 1907 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meltzer/Jerome Greene exchange re Meltzer election to membership in the German Academy of Natural Science, in Halle, 1911 August 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Engl: "Publications from the Department of Physiology and Pharmacology of the RIMR", 1912 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meltzer/Mr. Greene re exhibit at Congress of Hygiene, 1912 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Henry James] /Starr J. Murphy, re patenting of Dr. Meltzer's apparatus for Artificial respiration, 1913 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clipping. S.J. Meltzer, "The Deplorable Contract between Intranational and International Ethics and the Mission of Medical Science and Medical Men" Science 41 (1915) 515-524 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Henry James], "Notes on Dr. Meltzer's Paper", 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meltzer/Henry James, response to James, 1915 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Translations of letters to Meltzer re "Medical Brotherhood" from:
    - Axel Johannsen, 1915 September 29
    - F.V. Quervain, 1915 September 28
    - Karl Petren, 1915 September 27
    - CV Monakow, 1915 September 25
  - Meltzer/Henry James, re "shock" and work of F.C. Mann, extract of letter from Meltzer/Flexner, re demonstration at Joint Meeting of the Medical Societies of the counties of Allegany, Genesee, Livingston and Wyoming, 1916 May 1 circa 1916 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re Meltzer portrait, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer, re Meltzer demonstration to Dr. Carrel's classes, 1917 October 10 (?) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/Dr. Prudden, re death of Dr. Taylor, 1918 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/Flexner, re retirement, 1919 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/Flexner, recommending O.H. Robertson be given a Gates' Insufflation apparatus for use in the "China Medical Board School", 1919 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/T.M. Prudden, re Meltzer's status at Institute, 1919 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/Flexner, re final report and contributions "Report of Dr. S.J. Meltzer presented at the Meeting, April 17, 1920", 1920 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bus. Mgr. /Harry J. Dunham, re pharyngeal insufflations apparatus, 1920 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meltzer/Flexner, re salary, 1920 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Posthumous correspondence, 1920-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes: Funeral arrangements, memorials in honor of Dr. Meltzer, acknowledgments from the Meltzer family, photograph of official RIMR tribute in calligraphy, signed by Jacques Loeb, P.A. Levene, Alfred E. Cohn and presented at meeting of Board of Scientific Directors, January 15, 1921. Also includes New York Times obituary notice, December 18, 1922 (original and photocopy).
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Portrait of Dr. Meltzer painted by Adolph Borie, 1917; 1 photograph of painting
  - Laboratory group, partial identification, undated; 2 photographs
  - Dr. Meltzer, photographic portrait of, undated; Multiple copies, in various sizes
  - Photographic portrait by Dorris U. Jaeger, 1919
    Donated to the University by Richard Goldsmith in 1975.
- Reprints, 1909-1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes: Undated, "A Sketch Containing the Essentials of Any Apparatus for Intratracheal Insufflation".